I kind of want to segue into this other
topic that again I've been wanting to
speak to someone like yourself about is
this idea of growth hormone. And one
thing I've been talking about recently
because it comes up a lot in my
consultations and I started using it
myself about 6 months ago. At first I
wasn't consistent with it because it was
a pain in the ass, but then I got
consistent with it and it's what I'm
kind of calling this idea of like the
TRT of growth hormone. you know, what's
the using a growth hormone protocol
that's not, you know, super
physiological bodybuilding amount, but
kind of going what's the optimum amount
of growth hormone that a healthy man can
benefit from that's not going to cause
side effects that's going to support
health. And at least in in Australia and
in Europe, I think it would be more
common if it wasn't cost prohibitive.
But in in some of these countries more
so than others, it's definitely a
premium, but it's doable for a lot of
people. So, I guess my my kind of
question for you is what kind of person
could benefit from augmenting a TRT
protocol with optimizing their growth
hormone levels? And what types of, you
know, starting dosing or average dosing
do you kind of see with that? Another
great question. I just from the uh
circumstances of of my history, I have
dealt with human growth hormone a lot on
on a lot of levels and to a large
extent. So human growth hormone is
incredibly beneficial. It's another
stigmatized hormone in the United
States. It's actually it was actually
sent into a higher FDA regulatory
category so that it can only be
prescribed for a very parochial set of
circumstances. again. So, the the FDA, a
non-elected body, has somehow kind of
put it into almost a controlled
substance type category, but whatever.
We we'll go into the benefits of it. Um,
so, and you know, it was stigmatized.
There was, again, we for a lot of these
peptides, a lot of these beneficial
compounds, we always have to have the
alarmist doctors or somebody alarmist
from the medical community say, "Well,
it could cause cancer. It may cause
cancer. We don't know." So then that
scared everybody away from HD. It's no
evidence that it causes any kind of
cancer. It's incredibly beneficial. So
if we look at what human growth hormone
does, right? And in the evolutionary
mechanism of human growth hormone, we
can see that especially in present day,
it's very beneficial and it's what we
want. And and I believe just like
testosterone and certainly at a certain
point, everybody should be taking it.
Well, not only does it regenerate every
organ, let's just say that it
regenerates, it stimulates mito and and
for cell proliferation and regeneration
of all the organs. You notice it because
they say that it makes you look younger,
right? And the epidermis is the biggest
organ and it does. It it makes your skin
actually look bit better. That, you
know, that's one of the the organ
functions, but huge benefit. Let's start
talking about what what most people are
looking for when they take HGH. That's
kind of atapost tissue has HGH receptors
that forces them into lipolysis. Now
when we have uh lipolysis our blood is
flowing with with triglycerides free
triglycerides and this attenuates the
insulin process right so now our body
can't use glucose we and we're forced to
use our fat stores as a primary source
of energy over the glucose in our blood.
Now this process what we have to think
of is we evolved mechanisms to deal with
the caveman type days right in an
environment that did not have a surplus
of food when our our bodies first will
go through when when we're starving kind
of right our bodies will go through a
period of gluconneogenesis where we're
actually burning muscle mass or proteins
as a primary source of energy over our
fat stores. We conserve fat stores as
kind of a final source of energy. When
this starts happening, after a time our
body will increase human growth hormone,
which will then force the energy
transfer into using fat stores as a
primary source of energy. This is kind
of the conserve muscle mass and start
burning fat. And that's kind of like one
of the the processes of it. And it's
it's beneficial now that we're in an in
since the industrial revolution and um
processed foods and now we're in an
environment with superolous amount of
food um infinite amount of food and
energy. It's actually preferred. Like we
should be existing in in a state where
we're using fat stores as a primary
source of energy. The problems with
metabolic disorder and insulin
resistance are just prevalent. So here's
the problem now. When we increase the
triglycerides in our blood and attenuate
the insulin process, now it's easy for
our glucose to raise. A lot of people
say, "Oh no, HGH causes diabetes or it
causes your glucose to raise." Well,
that's not it doesn't cause that. It's a
side effect of you switching energy
pathways and using your fat stores. Now,
you're not using the glucose in your
blood, so it's easier to build up. So,
we just have to really watch our diet
when we're on HGH. That's it. Um, long
acting carbs, reduce the amount of
carbs, no sugars. Sugars are out. You
really have to just improve your diet um
to to deal with that human growth
hormone. But if you can do that, then
you have massive benefits from human
growth hormone. We're talking about not
only the regeneration of all the organs,
but really getting lean and for really
fine-tuning your body. Like I used to
tell people, it almost makes you look
like you're carved out of marble. Really
the Yeah. subcutaneous fat and
everything. So, now let's talk about
dosages. And and here's another problem
is that there's too low doses. And and
there's really no there's no such thing
as too much HGH. Honestly, you really
can't take too much. It's not like
testosterone. You're not going to take
too much and there's going to be adverse
side effects. There's no amount that you
can take. That's too much. So, what I
always tell people is just take what you
can afford. So, when we're thinking
about a starting dose, and I don't think
it makes any sense, it it barely makes
sense to take two IUs per day. That
would be like just a replacement dose.
And if we're looking for any kind of
enhancement, then we need to take more
than two IUs per day. So, I would say
start at three. Um, even for women, two
or three for women as well. Women do
really well on human growth hormone, by
the way. really well. I would say like
if you're looking for any kind of
enhancement, three, if you're just
looking for a replacement dose, two IUs
per day and then it just goes up from
there. It's not like you're going to
notice a huge difference from 10 to 20
IU. Well, depending on the person. Some
people actually do, but again, take as
much as you can afford. That's that's
what I always tell people. Yeah, that's
definitely a factor, isn't it? It's um
it's interesting that you bring that up
in terms of those dosages because when
um I' I've I've got a friend and I I'll
I'll send this to her and and she showed
me that she had one of the most
remarkable health transformations that
I'd ever seen. I mean, you would have
thought that she'd had a whole bunch of
cosmetic surgeries done and she took uh
two units of HGH in the morning and then
again at night, so four per day and
combined it with very high dose
magnesium. So I I think she was using a
blend to be able to tolerate very high
doses in conjunction with diet and
exercise almost unrecognizable as
opposed to like absolutely incredible.
And that's it. It's it's definitely the
problem with with growth hormone, isn't
it? That because because it's so
expensive per unit, you want to get away
with taking as little as possible. But
what I also tell people is going well
because you've now got to, you know, pin
one extra thing as a daily subcutaneous
injection. You don't want to take too
little that it's a waste of time because
then that's a real pain in your
schedule. So um okay that's that's
interesting. Sorry I apologize. One
thing I forgot there is is people aren't
sure when to take it. When do I take it?
We over discussing this a lot with with
some of the the other my bodybuilder
friends are really in the know and have
really seen this a lot. We've kind of
come up with the probably the best is
just one bulis at night. Um sometimes uh
HGH can can make you tired can cause
some fatigue and it's a hormone so it it
can cause some inflammation. That's
another thing too. It can cause some
inflammation again and that's also what
causes like a lot of people complain of
wrist like wrist numbness, right? And
that's just an inflammatory response and
you should be happy that you're getting
that because it means you have good
stuff and it's working. But that's
another thing that tends to abate over
time if we can just outlast the
inflammatory response. The renin
andotensin eldoststerone system should
normalize and the um some of those
effects should abate. Sometimes it can
make you tired which is why we say just
take it at night. take one bulis at
night and that's the best methodology
we've seen. Now individual responses
I've seen it wake people up in that case
I'll be I'd switch that person say okay
you take it in the morning because it's
obviously having a stimulatory effect
for you most people it's the opposite so
start off taking one bulis at night
change that if necessary so my personal
follow-up question for that which I'd
also like to think that other people
might have watching this as well and
again when we spoke before we recorded I
said that the area that I probably know
the least about in this field is HGH And
one of the things that you know you hear
things and you go you know is that a
myth? Is that just [__] that people
parrot or is there substance to that?
But kind of touching on what you were
saying before about carbohydrates. I'd
always heard that you want to take it
away from insulin spikes. So if you have
someone who let's say eats you know in
the evening you know quite close to
bedtime and then maybe does some fasting
in the morning until noon or something
like that. Would it still be beneficial
for that individual to take it before
bed or should they take it in the
morning? Yeah, that's a great point.
Because of it switches that energy
pathway, the the the the spike in
glucose may not the the insulin insulin
response will be attenuated. So your
glucose may may go high. So So you're
right, take it away from when you're
eating the when your glucose is going to
spike or the insulin response is going
to happen. Yeah. If you eat in the
evening and and you need to keep it away
and you need to take it at a time more
when you're fasting, try that. And but
but also be aware that you may get a
little fatigued and if you do then maybe
changing things around to take that at
night to just mitigate the tiredness or
fatigue side effect that can occur.
Yeah, that that makes a lot of sense to
me. Like one thing I found with
pregnenolone, for example, is that like
most people find that it makes them
tired, but a decent minority of people
find it stimulating. Um, so then you've
got to find a way to make it work. And
you know, that makes sense to me in
terms of being like, well, you know,
take it away from the insulin spike, but
then if it does make you tired, maybe,
you know, eating before you go to bed
isn't ideal anyway. So now you have an
excuse to kind of change that around
anyway. So that that makes a lot of
sense. Yeah, that that's that's very
interesting.
Hey,
hey, hey.